Guide to the Willis Smith Papers, 1919-1954 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Willis Smith papers 1919-1954 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Smith, Willis, 1887-1953
130.4 linear feet Extent: 97,813 Items
Lawyer and U.S. Senator, 1950-1953, from Raleigh (Wake Co.), N.C. Personal, political and professional papers, including correspondence, notes and speeches, financial papers, clippings, printed material, pictures, and other miscellaneous papers. The major portion of the collection consists of personal papers; the office files from his years as U.S. Senator, much of which is routine correspondence; files kept while Smith was president of the American Bar Association, 1945-1946; papers relating to other legal organizations; and files pertaining to his service as chairman of the Board of Trustees of Duke University, 1947-1953.
RL.01223
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Willis Smith Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1954.
Collection Overview
Personal, political, and professional papers of Willis Smith, Sr., lawyer and U.S. senator, 1950-1953, spanning the years 1919-1954. Collection includes correspondence, notes and speeches, financial papers, clippings, printed material, pictures, and other miscellaneous papers. The major portion of the collection consists of personal papers; the office files from his years as U. S. senator, much of which is routine correspondence; files kept by Smith while he was president of the American Bar Association, 1945-1946; papers relating to other legal organizations, including the International Bar Association, the North Carolina State Bar Association, the Wake County Bar Association, and the International Association of Insurance Counsel; and files pertaining to his service as chairman of the board of trustees of Duke University, 1947-1953. There is also material on the Patrick Henry Memorial Foundation, the Raleigh Chamber of Commerce, the American Counsel Association, the American Judicature Society, the Attorney General's Advisory Committee on Citizenship, Louisburg College (Louisburg, North Carolina), the American Law Institute, the Presidential Memorial Commission, the Association of Life Insurance Counsel, the President's Amnesty Board, the National Probation and Parole Association, the Nuremburg trials, the Interparliamentary Union, the Smithsonian Institution, the United States Territorial Expansion Memorial Commission, and Alben W. Barkley.
Subject Headings
American Bar Association; Duke University. Board of Trustees; Bar associations -- North Carolina; Bar associations -- United States; Lawyers -- North Carolina -- Raleigh; Lawyers -- Political activity; Legislators -- Correspondence; Legislators -- United States; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1953
Contents of Collection
- Personal Papers Series, 1918-1953 and undated, (20 boxes)
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1919-1953
    - 1919-1938 (Box 1)
    - 1939-1941 (Box 2)
    - 1942-1943 Sept. (Box 3)
    - 1943 Oct.-1945 Feb. (Box 4)
    - 1945 Mar.-1946 Feb. (Box 5)
    - 1946 Mar.-Oct. (Box 6)
    - 1946 Nov.-1947 June (Box 7)
    - 1947 July-1948 May (Box 8)
    - 1948 June-1949 Feb. (Box 9)
    - 1949 Mar.-1950 June (Box 10)
    - 1950 July-1951 Mar. (Box 11)
    - 1951 Apr.-Aug. (Box 12)
    - 1951 Sept.-1952 Jan. (Box 13)
    - 1952 Feb.-Aug. (Box 14)
    - 1952 Sept.-1953 Mar. 20 (Box 15)
    - 1953 Mar. 21-Dec. (Box 16)
  - Financial Papers Subseries, 1934-1951 and undated (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous Subseries, 1918-1952 and undated (Box 17)
  - Speeches Subseries, 1936-1953 and undated (Box 18)
  - Clippings Subseries, 1940-1952 and undated (Box 18)
  - Printed Material Subseries
    - 1922-1946 Nov. (Box 19)
    - 1946 Nov.-1953 and undated (Box 20)
  - Pictures Subseries (Box 20)
- Political Papers Series, 1926-1954 and undated, bulk 1950s, (75 boxes)
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1926-1953, bulk 1950s
    - 1926-1949 (Box 21)
    - 1950 Jan.-Dec. 4 (Box 22)
    - 1950 Dec. 5-21 (Box 23)
    - 1950 Dec. 22-1951 Jan. 11 (Box 24)
    - 1951 Jan. 12-21 (Box 25)
    - 1951 Jan. 22-31 (Box 26)
    - 1951 Feb. 1-12 (Box 27)
    - 1951 Feb. 13-21 (Box 28)
    - 1951 Feb. 22-Mar. 3 (Box 29)
    - 1951 Mar. 4-13 (Box 30)
    - 1951 Mar. 14-25 (Box 31)
    - 1951 Mar. 26-Apr. 6 (Box 32)
    - 1951 Apr. 7-20 (Box 33)
    - 1951 Apr. 21-May (Box 34)
    - 1951 May 2-10 (Box 35)
    - 1951 May 11-23 (Box 36)
    - 1951 May 24-June 5 (Box 37)
    - 1951 June 6-17 (Box 38)
    - 1951 June 18-24 (Box 39)
    - 1951 June 25-30 (Box 40)
    - 1951 July 1-12 (Box 41)
    - 1951 July 13-23 (Box 42)
    - 1951 July 24-Aug. 2 (Box 43)
    - 1951 Aug. 3-14 (Box 44)
    - 1951 Aug. 15-26 (Box 45)
    - 1951 Aug. 27-Sept. 2 (Box 46)
    - 1951 Sept. 3-11 (Box 47)
    - 1951 Sept. 12-21 (Box 48)
    - 1951 Sept. 24-Oct. 10 (Box 49)
    - 1951 Oct. 11-29 (Box 50)
    - 1951 Oct. 30-Nov. 19 (Box 51)
    - 1951 Nov. 20-Dec. 9 (Box 52)
    - 1951 Dec. 10-31 (Box 53)
    - 1952 Jan. 1-9 (Box 54)
    - 1952 Jan. 10-17 (Box 55)
    - 1952 Jan. 18-28 (Box 56)
    - 1952 Jan. 29-Feb. 10 (Box 57)
    - 1952 Feb. 11-21 (Box 58)
    - 1952 Feb. 22-Mar. 3 (Box 59)
    - 1952 Mar. 4-18 (Box 60)
    - 1952 Mar. 19-Apr. 2 (Box 61)
    - 1952 Apr. 3-18 (Box 62)
    - 1952 Apr. 19-28 (Box 63)
    - 1952 Apr. 29-May 12 (Box 64)
    - 1952 May 13-27 (Box 65)
    - 1952 May 28-June 9 (Box 66)
    - 1952 June 10-24 (Box 67)
    - 1952 June 25-Aug. 6 (Box 68)
    - 1952 Aug. 7-Nov. 3 (Box 69)
    - 1952 Nov. 4-1953 Jan. 12 (Box 70)
    - 1953 Jan. 13-Feb. 16 (Box 71)
    - 1953 Feb. 17-Mar. 16 (Box 72)
    - 1953 Mar. 17-Apr. 13 (Box 73)
    - 1953 Apr. 14-May 7 (Box 74)
    - 1953 May 8-28 (Box 75)
    - 1953 May 29-June 21 (Box 76)
    - 1953 June 22-Dec. (Box 77)
  - Political Speeches Subseries
    - 1931-1953 (Box 77)
    - Undated (Box 78)
    - Notes for speeches, 1932-1939 and undated (Box 78)
  - Miscellany Subseries
    - Department of Defense, 1950-1952 (Box 79)
    - Office of Alien Property, 1946-1953 and undated (Box 79-80)
    - Other Papers, 1927-1951 May (Box 81)
    - 1951 June-1952 Feb. (Box 82)
    - 1952 Mar.-1953 Feb. 19 (Box 83)
    - 1953 Feb. 20-Apr. 20 (Box 84)
    - 1953 Apr. 21-Dec. and undated (Box 85)
    - Undated (Box 86)
  - Clippings Subseries
    - 1927-1931 (Box 86)
    - 1932-1950 June (Box 87)
    - 1950 June (Folders III-IX) (Box 88)
    - 1950 July-1953 and undated (Box 89)
  - Printed Material Subseries
    - 1920-1943 (Box 89)
    - 1944-1950 (Box 90)
    - 1951 Jan.-May 15 (Box 91)
    - 1951 May 16-Dec. (Box 92)
    - 1952 Jan.-May (Box 93)
    - 1952 June-1953 Feb. (Box 94)
    - 1953 Mar.-1954 and undated (Box 95)
- Bar Association Papers Series, 1925-1953 and undated, (29 boxes)
  - International Bar Association Subseries, 1946-1950
    - 1946-1950 (Box 96)
  - American Bar Association Subseries, 1926-1953 and undated
    - Correspondence
      - 1926-1938 Feb. (Box 97)
      - 1938 Mar.-1940 (Box 98)
      - 1941-1942 June (Box 99)
      - 1942 July-1943 July (Box 100)
      - 1943 Aug.-1944 Apr. (Box 101)
      - 1944 May-1945 Mar. (Box 102)
      - 1945 Apr.-Aug. (Box 103)
      - 1945 Sept.-1946 Jan. 17 (Box 104)
      - 1946 Jan. 18-Mar. 18 (Box 105)
      - 1946 Mar. 19-June 11 (Box 106)
      - 1946 July-Aug. 12 (Box 107)
      - 1946 Aug. 13-Sept. (Box 108)
      - 1946 Oct.-Dec. (Box 109)
      - 1947-1948 (Box 110)
      - 1949-1953 (Box 111)
    - Speeches and Notes (Box 111)
    - Papers, American Bar Association Journal (Box 111)
    - Financial Papers, 1940-1947 and undated (Box 112)
    - Miscellany
      - 1935-1939 (Box 112)
      - 1940-1942 (Box 113)
      - 1943-1944 Sept. (Box 114)
      - 1944 Oct.-1946 Apr. (Box 115)
      - 1946 May-Dec. (Box 116)
      - 1947-1952 (Box 117)
      - undated (Box 118)
    - Printed Material
      - 1937-1942 (Box 118)
      - 1943-1945 Sept. (Box 119)
      - 1945 Oct.-1946 (Box 120)
      - 1947-1952 (Box 121)
    - Clippings (Box 121)
    - Pictures (Box 121)
  - North Carolina State Bar Association Subseries, 1938-1953
    - Correspondence
      - 1938-1942 Feb. (Box 122)
      - 1942 Apr.-1946 (Box 123)
      - 1947-1953 (Box 124)
    - Miscellany (Box 124)
    - Printed Materials (Box 124)
    - Pictures (Box 124)
  - Wake County Bar Association Subseries, 1925-1953
    - Wake County Bar Association materials (Box 124)
- Duke University Series, 1919-1953 and undated, (12 boxes)
  - Correspondence Subseries
    - 1919-1930 (Box 125)
    - 1931-1935 (Box 126)
    - 1936-1940 (Box 127)
    - 1941-1946 (Box 128)
    - 1947 (Box 129)
    - 1948 Jan.-Sept. (Box 130)
    - 1948 Oct.-1949 Oct. (Box 131)
    - 1949 Nov.-1951 Sept. (Box 132)
    - 1951 Oct.-1953 (Box 133)
  - Financial Papers Subseries, 1923-1952 and undated
    - Financial papers (Box 134)
  - Miscellany Subseries
    - 1919-1949 (Box 134)
    - 1949-1953 and undated (Box 135)
  - Clippings Subseries, 1924-1951 and undated
    - Clippings (Box 135)
  - Printed Material Subseries
    - 1919-1934 (Box 135)
    - 1935-1953 and undated (Box 136)
- International Association of Insurance Counsel Series, 1933-1953 and undated, (6 boxes)
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1933-1953
    - 1933-1940 (Box 137)
    - 1941 Sept.-1942 June (Box 138)
    - 1942 July-1943 July (Box 139)
    - 1943 Aug.-1953 (Box 140)
  - Miscellany Subseries, 1934-1950 and undated
    - 1934-1938 (Box 140)
    - 1940-1942 (Box 141)
    - 1943-1950 and undated (Box 142)
  - Printed Material Subseries
    - Printed materials (Box 142)
- Other Professional Files Series, 1932-1951, (7 boxes)
  - Patrick Henry Memorial Foundation, 1946-1949 (Box 143)
  - Raleigh Chamber of Commerce, 1941-1948 (Box 143)
  - American Counsel Association, 1932-1951 (Box 143)
  - American Judicature Society (Box 144)
  - Attorney General's Advisory Committee on Citizenship (Box 144)
  - Louisburg College (Box 144)
  - American Law Institute (Box 145)
  - Presidential Memorial Commission (Box 145)
  - Association of Life Insurance Counsel, 1936-1951 (Box 146)
  - President's Amnesty Board
    - Correspondence, 1946-1948 (Box 146)
    - Miscellany (Box 147)
    - Printed Material (Box 147)
  - National Probation and Parole Association, 1945-1950 (Box 148)
  - Smithsonian Institution (Box 156)
  - U.S. Territorial Expansion Memorial Commission (Box 156)
  - Alben W. Barkley (Box 156)
- Nuremberg Trials Series, 1945-1953, (2 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1953 (Box 149)
  - Miscellany, 1945-1948 (Box 149)
  - Speeches, clippings, printed material, and pictures (Box 150)
- Interparliamentary Union Series, 1922-1953 and undated, (5 boxes)
  - Correspondence Subseries
    - 1930-1946 (Box 151)
    - 1947-1951 (Box 152)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 153)
  - Miscellany Subseries
    - 1922-1949 (Box 153)
    - 1950 and undated (Box 154)
  - Pictures Subseries (Box 154)
  - Printed Material Subseries
    - 1935-1948 (Box 154)
    - 1949-1953 and undated (Box 155)
- Oversize Materials
  Consists of clippings, 1950, and campaign material.
  - Oversize items (Oversize-box 5)